<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects | Scott Ogletree</title>
    <link>https://scottogletree.com/project/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://scottogletree.com/project/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© 2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://scottogletree.com/images/icon_hu2b9cc5b7fa65526660959abbc390ca92_13336_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://scottogletree.com/project/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using secondary data to examine whether a programme of physical and social interventions in urban forests enhances community health and wellbeing.</title>
      <link>https://scottogletree.com/project/wiat/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://scottogletree.com/project/wiat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;£240,622
Feb 21 - Dec 23&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Research Fellow - June 2021 to December 2022; Co-I from January 2023&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This research addresses urgent questions faced by Scottish Forestry, alongside forestry agencies across the rest of the UK, Europe and internationally, who want to know how they can respond positively to global challenges for sustainability and human health while satisfying demands for more tree cover. In addition, public health policy-makers and planners, land managers, spatial planners and land development agencies and third sector organisations want to know how to invest scarce resources in ways that maximise benefits for people as well as planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So our focus is on urban forestry and how to provide better evidence of the contributions it can make to human wellbeing, child development and health equity. Our increasingly urban population is experiencing rising levels of mental illness and non-communicable disease; in addition, there is concern about the long-term effects of urban living on the kinds of environments children experience. There is evidence that access to natural environments such as woodlands can offer health benefits, especially in relation to mental wellbeing, and support healthy child development. In addition, it appears that more socially disadvantaged people may gain most from improved opportunities to visit and enjoy urban forests and other natural environments. We plan to provide evidence on the effectiveness of practical ways in which forestry can be used to benefit such populations. Our study examines whether existing programmes for urban forestry, such as Scottish Forestry&amp;rsquo;s (formerly known as Forestry Commission Scotland) Woods In and Around Towns (WIAT) programme, are effective in their aims of improving community wellbeing and quality of life by bringing neglected urban woodland near deprived urban communities into active management and working with local people to help them use their local woodland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are taking advantage of new opportunities to link existing population, health and child development data for a large number of people, together with data on WIAT projects that have been undertaken near where these people live at any point in a ten year period (2005-2015). This will be done in a secure and ethically approved manner so that there is no risk of individuals or their personal data being identifiable. It is an exciting opportunity because of the high quality data available across a representative sample of Scotland&amp;rsquo;s population; for the first time we can link information such as prescriptions data for anti-depressants, or child gross and fine motor skills development, with data on the location, cost, timing and extent of a national urban forestry programme. The results will indicate whether, for example, the extent of new footpaths and improved forest entrances, alongside activities to bring children and adults into the forest, makes a difference to health and child development outcomes for people living near the urban forest. We&amp;rsquo;ll look at whether benefits from WIAT are experienced only by those living very close to the forest, how long it takes for any benefits to appear after a WIAT project is completed, whether benefits are sustained and whether there are differences in benefit according to people&amp;rsquo;s age, gender, or socio-economic status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our findings will be published not only in academic journals but also in ways that are most helpful for different stakeholders, from forest and land managers and environmental agencies to health and child development policymakers. We will be working closely with Scottish Forestry and other public agencies across the UK and Europe to find the best ways of doing this. We&amp;rsquo;ll also make our findings accessible to local communities and the wider public. Ultimately, we hope that urban communities will benefit from better evidence as to how government departments and public and private agencies can support people&amp;rsquo;s access to urban forests to support their, and their children&amp;rsquo;s, wellbeing and quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greenspace and Telomere Length</title>
      <link>https://scottogletree.com/project/greenspace_telomere/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://scottogletree.com/project/greenspace_telomere/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We received a pilot project grant for $36,000 to investigate the relationship between greenspace and telomere length in the NHANES data. I led the conceptualization, writing, and submittal of this project to the Center for Human Health and the Environment at NC State. Along with Dr. Aaron Hipp, Dr. David Reif, and Dr. Lin Yang we will be looking at what can be learned about how our environment influences health at the level of DNA.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenspaces, composed of vegetation such as lawns, street trees, and parks, are associated with a variety of benefits to mental and physical health. The effect of green, vegetated landscapes on human health has been investigated from the level of specific health behaviors and outcomes, self-reported measures of well being, and quality of life, but little work has been able to identify biological mechanisms behind these associations. Our proposed project will investigate a pathway that greenspace environments might influence health at the cellular level, through the preservation of telomere length. Telomeres are structures on the ends of DNA and play a role in cell regeneration and aging. The length of telomeres can be impacted by stressors in the environment and could be an epigenetic factor in disease and individual health. Greenspace is an environmental condition that varies across residential areas and could influence telomere length through stress regulation, physical activity opportunities, air quality improvements, or other impacts. Little research has been done on the relationship that environmental greenspace may have on telomere length, and therefore disease, cellular health, and aging.
This project will use data from National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey (NHANES) to establish an initial investigation of the relationship. NHANES 1999-2002 collected biospecimens from which telomere length was determined for approximately 7,500 individuals. Using the extensive examination and laboratory data from NHANES combined with time-matched environmental data on greenspace exposure from satellite imagery, this study will serve as a pilot project to investigate the association of the greenspace environment and telomere length. Participant residential geolocation is restricted in the NHANES data, but is available from the National Center for Health Statistics Research Data Centers. Accessing this location data will allow for measurement of local greenspace exposure to combine with available NHANES data on telomere length and covariates to facilitate analysis.
Findings of this retrospective study will inform the research gaps and aims to submit an NIH R01 or R21 focused on the effects of environmental greenspace on public health and telomere length. The pilot study will serve as a means of revealing potential questions and causal mechanisms to inform a future study as well as provide new cross-university collaborations between Parks, Recreation, and Tourism Management and Biological Sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PARC3 - Physical Activity and Recreation in Children in Communities of Color</title>
      <link>https://scottogletree.com/project/parc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://scottogletree.com/project/parc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of my postdoc at NC State I am working on the PARC3 - Physical Activity and Recreation in Children in Communities of Color led by Dr. Aaron Hipp and Dr. Myron Floyd. The project involves observations and surveys at parks in New York City and Raleigh-Durham. The bulk of the work was done in 2017 and 2018 and we are analyzing data and writing up our findings as part of my work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is part of a broader effort studying physical activity that was funded by the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Project Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Public parks represent key settings for promoting physical activity among children who are least likely to be active and most likely to be overweight or obese. Parks are generally widely available, offering programs and facilities targeted to young children. Because they are public entities, municipal parks can be influenced by a range of policy actions that affect how they are designed, located, programmed, as well as how they are managed and maintained. Describing park use patterns among different racial and ethnic groups, particularly in low-income neighborhoods, can inform planning decisions on how to meet diverse recreation needs and advance public health goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Children in kindergarten through 5th grade (as of Spring 2017) are the target population along with one parent or primary caregiver (child/parent dyads). Racial and ethnic populations include African American, Asian, and Latino children and caregivers. Data collection focuses on 20 parks in New York City (Asian and Latino) and 20 neighborhood parks in Raleigh-Durham (African American and Latino). Systematic observations using SOPARC are being used to measure children’s use of parks and park-based physical activity across all 40 parks. Parks, as well as surrounding neighborhoods, are being audited to identify and describe environmental supports for, and barriers to, physical activity. Individual-level physical activity and location data are obtained from in-park surveys, accelerometers, and GPS. A brief telephone survey of neighborhoods near the study parks will identify types of park attributes parents look for when making decisions about their children’s use of parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://paresearchcenter.org/project-profiles/nc-state-project-profile/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PARC Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Combining System for Observing Play and Recreation in Communities (SOPARC)</title>
      <link>https://scottogletree.com/project/soparc_combine/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://scottogletree.com/project/soparc_combine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;System for Observing Play and Recreation in Communities (SOPARC) is a tool for measuring activity in parks. Researchers have used SOPARC in a variety of setting and for this project we are combining the data from 3 separate studies done in New York City. Despite an established protocol each study adjusted the SOPARC tool to their project. We hope to be able to combine each dataset into one grand dataset to understand broader patterns in park use in NYC.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project Ideas</title>
      <link>https://scottogletree.com/project/internal-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://scottogletree.com/project/internal-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defining Greenspace 2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bike share during COVID19&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Causal analysis of &amp;lsquo;Every Kid in a Park&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changes due to Falls Park in Greeenville, SC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Geography of Outdoor Retail&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mountain bike deserts&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Analysis of comments about NPS fee hike in 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mapping academic connections&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greenways and property values in Raleigh, NC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Determining near park population in the USA&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;more&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
